A Guide to the General records from the Virginia Land Office, 1670-1806
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
General records from the Virginia Land Office, 1670-1806
The Library of Virginia
LOI 104
.45 cu. ft. (1 box)
Virginia. Northern Neck Land Office.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred in 1948 from the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Richmond, VA 23219.
Biographical Information
General records, 1670-1806, including correspondence, depositions over land disputes, bills of sale, lists, and surveys for land in Augusta, Culpeper, Frederick, Loudoun, Orange, Prince William, and Stafford Counties, Virginia; and Hampshire and Hardy Counties, West Virginia. It is unknown why these records were grouped together.
Scope and Content
The Northern Neck Land Office controlled 5,282,000 acres in land grants located between the Rappahannock and Potomac rivers, which were given to seven loyal supporters of King Charles II. Agents of the Northern Neck Proprietary issued the first land grant in 1690.
To obtain land in the Northern Neck persons purchased warrants which specified the exact location of the land desired. A warrant was taken to a surveyor, and the land desired was surveyed. The plat and any accompanying papers were returned to the proprietor's office from which, if no discrepancy existed and no conflicting claim was presented, a grant was issued. The survey was filed and the grant recorded before delivery. Unlike the colonial Land Office, the Northern Neck Land Office did not annually destroy plats.
The Proprietary operated until the death of Lord Fairfax in 1781. For the next thirty years, however, the ownership was in dispute. Fairfax family interest was terminated in 1808 when the last surviving heir sold his title to his remaining manor to a syndicate.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Ashbrooke, widow: Warrant for 100 acres in [Hampshire or Hardy] County, West Virginia, 1753 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Banden, Rynard: Survey for 400 acres in Augusta and Frederick Counties, Virginia, 1750 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cady, Elesebeth: Assign estate and rights to lands to James Cadey, 1762 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Calvert, Humphrey: Survey for 400 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1752 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Caton, Thomas: Letter to G.W. Fairfax regarding land in dispute between James Hogland and John [Sherow?], 1752 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Caton, Thomas: Papers relating to 300 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, in dispute between Samuel Harris and Thomas Caton, 1759-1763 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chamberlin, Richard: Summons to answer petition of William Muirhead, Loudoun County, Virginia, 1766 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Colclough, John: Bill of sale to Alexander Watson and Jno. Boulton for 100 acres in Stafford County, Virginia, 1670 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Connell, William: Letter to William Fairfax regarding the sale of land, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Crawford, Valentine: Survey for 100 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1752 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Currell, Abraham: Surveys for 34 and 70 acres in Lancaster County, Virginia, 1722 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Denton, James: Bill of sale to Patrick Kiney for 300 acres in [Augusta?] County, Virginia, 1754 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Dewit, Charles: Survey for 2640 acres in Orange County, Virginia, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Farrington, Samuel and William Warden: Depositions from William Hughes, William Naylor, Richard Arnold, and Henry Oldacre regarding land in dispute in Frederick County, Virginia, 1752 December 19-29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Farrow, Abraham: Account of debts to Stephen Clayton regarding Harwood's escheat, Prince William County, Virginia, 1731 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Feely, Michael and Timothy: Letter of attorney to Patrick Daly, Frederick County, Virginia, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Gray, David: Papers regarding the sale of lands to John Gray, Berkeley County, [West] Virginia, 1797-1806 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Green, Charles: Letter to William Fairfax regarding medical treatment for an injured leg, [1742?] (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Green, William, Survey for 197 acres in Frederick County, Virginia 1750 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Grigsbey, Richard: Survey and warrant for 400 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1752 February-March (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Guinn, John, Promissory note to Anthony Seill for in Berkeley County, West Virginia, 1769 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Harden, John: Survey for 407 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Henlen, Michael: Survey for 372 acres in Augusta County, Virginia, 1749 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Henry, Conrod: Oath of Catrout Bomgardner, former wife of Conrod Henry, declaring Barara Miller as heir to Conrod Henry, Hampshire County, West Virginia, 1776 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Higgins, Margrett: Letter to Col. Martin, regarding land to which her late husband, Thomas Higgins, had a right, but was now in the possession of Nathaniel Bell and Jacob Rush, 1764 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Howard, Matthew: Assignment of land rights to Robert Willson, 1754 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Jacobus, John Daniel: Survey and warrant for 302 acres in Culpeper County, Virginia, 1752 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Kirkendal, John: Survey for 400 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1749/1750 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Lewis, Thomas: Survey by Guy Broadwater of land in a dispute with William Fairfax, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- McDonnald, James: Survey for 400 acres in Augusta County, Virginia, 1750 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Mercer, Edward: Survey for 96 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1753 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Moore, John: Receipt of Michael Holland's bond for 200 acres of land, 1743 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Naylor, William: Bond to Richard Arnold for 280 acres in Hampshire County, West Virginia, 1756 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Pope, Worden: Debt to George Gent for sundries, ca. 1746 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Queen [Quinn], Darby: Survey and warrant for 400 acres in Augusta County, Virginia, 1749 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Quitrents: Joseph [Dictron?] and Jacob Hite, 1739-1740 and 1769 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Rutherford, Thomas: Survey and warrant for 1121 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1750 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Sallars, George: Survey and warrant for 82 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1768 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Skinker, Samuel: Letter to William Fairfax asking for a deed, 1745 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Stephens, Lawrence: Letter and deed of gift to sons Peter, John, and Bryan Martin, for land [Sugar Hill], in Frederick County, Virginia, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Stephens, Lewis: Affidavit and bond for a transfer of land called Rough Bottom in Hampshire County, West Virginia, from Solomon Carpenter to Thomas Taylor to Christinia Linville to Lewis Stephens, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Stuart, Joseph: Survey for land in Frederick County, Virginia, 1763 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Thomas, John: Memorandum regarding the land of Edmond McGinnis in [Augusta?] County, Virginia, 1769 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Thomazin, Simon: Survey for 339 acres in Stafford County, Virginia, including a listing of heirs, 1709 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Vance, David: List for warrants, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Warner, John: Account of warrants in his hand when he died, 1741 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Weatherspoon, John: Proceedings of John Kennady regarding rights to land surveyed by John Mauzey; Arthur Dent serves for the orphan David Weatherspoon, 1766 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Wright, George: Survey for 400 acres in Frederick County, Virginia, 1751 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Wright, Isaac: Bond to George Potts for land in Frederick County, Virginia, 1752 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Misc.: List of fees paid to the Proprietors Office, 1753 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Misc.: Letter to an unknown uncle sent from Pennsylvania, 1756 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Misc.: James Compton receipt; sale of land to Robert Haroson; and notice about land belonging to John Simons and John West, Fairfax County, Virginia, 1747-1752 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Misc.: Fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)